Register of the William Patrick Clark papers
Hoover Institution Archives
William Patrick Clark papers
1966-2008
2016C19
Hoover Institution Archives
197 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 6 sound cassettes, 1 sound disc (72.5 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches and writings, memoranda, reports, studies, notes, legal and financial records, printed matter, and photographs relating to the gubernatorial administration of Ronald Reagan in California, and to foreign policy and public lands management during the presidential administration of Ronald Reagan.
Clark, William Patrick, 1931-2013.
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2016.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Biographical Note
1931 Born, Oxnard, California
1954-1956 U.S. Army service
1958 Admitted to California state bar
1967 Cabinet Secretary to Governor Ronald Reagan
1967-1969 Executive Secretary to Governor Ronald Reagan
1969-1971 Judge, San Luis Obispo County Superior Court
1971-1973 Associate Justice, California Second District Court of Appeals
1973-1981 Associate Justice, California Supreme Court
1981-1982 United States Deputy Secretary of State
1982-1983 National Security Adviser to President Ronald Reagan
1983-1985 United States Secretary of the Interior
1985-1990 Member, Rogers and Wells law firm
1985ff. Founder and Chief Executive Officer, Clark Company
2013 Died, Shandon, California
Scope and Content of Collection
William Patrick Clark, Jr. was a close associate of Ronald Reagan, whom he served during Reagan's terms both as Governor of California and as President of the United States. Clark grew up in Ventura County, California, where his father was a rancher and where his family had been pioneer settlers. Although he never graduated from college or from law school, Clark did pass the California state bar examination and began practice as a lawyer. His papers at the Hoover Institution Archives, acquired in 2016, are arranged according to periods of his life. Aside from two photographs the collection includes nothing from his pre-government life.
The California Governor's Office File documents Clark's first government service. Clark's involvement in Reagan's successful 1966 gubernatorial campaign led to the acquaintanceship of the two men and the development of a relationship that observers of Reagan characterized as exceptionally close. Clark was initially appointed Cabinet Secretary to the Governor when Reagan went to Sacramento, but was soon promoted to Executive Secretary to replace Philip Battaglia. The file covers the work of the Governor's Office during the first years of the Reagan governorship from 1967 to 1969, and the circumstances of Battaglia's departure.
Clark resigned from the Governor's Office in 1969 in order to accept a judicial appointment. This was the first of three successive appointments of Clark by Reagan, each at a higher level, that ultimately brought Clark to a seat on the California Supreme Court. Altogether he served twelve years (1969-1981) in a judicial capacity and ever afterwards was known as Judge Clark. This period of Clark's life is documented in the California Judicial File. The state Supreme Court was unusually contentious during the time of Clark's service and was often polarized between a liberal faction headed by Chief Justice Rose Bird (an appointee of Governor Jerry Brown) and a conservative faction of which Clark was a member. There is in particular a large quantity of material on the much-publicized case of People vs. Tanner (1978), in which the Court initially overturned a new state law mandating a prison sentence for use of a gun during the commission of a crime, and subsequently reversed itself.
When Reagan became President in 1981, he brought Clark to Washington, appointing him Deputy Secretary of State despite his lack of background in foreign affairs. Clark served under Secretary of State Alexander Haig and was often seen as a balance to Haig and as a man whose personal loyalty to the President was unquestioned. The appointment, which for the first time familiarized Clark with the international world of diplomacy, lasted for almost exactly one year. It is documented in the United States Department of State File.
Clark's next position, documented in the United States National Security Council File, was as National Security Adviser. Clark succeeded Richard V. Allen in this capacity in early 1982 and served almost two years, until November 1983. (Allen's papers are also in the Hoover Institution Archives.) Clark was generally seen as a voice for a hard-line foreign policy vis-a-vis the Soviet Union in the Reagan administration. This file, like the preceding one and the succeeding one, contains unclassified documents retained by Clark for personal use rather than official documents.
Clark's resignation as National Security Adviser in order to accept an appointment as Secretary of the Interior came as a surprise to most Washington observers. His final period of government service is documented in the United States Department of the Interior File. Clark's background as a Westerner and as an outdoorsman gave him considerable familiarity with many of the issues dealt with by this department. Clark served in this capacity for more than a year. Following Reagan's re-election and second inauguration, Clark resigned in February 1985 to leave government service and return to the private sector.
The Post-Government Service File documents the longest period of Clark's life and unsurprisingly is the largest series of the collection. Clark initially joined the prestigious Washington law firm of Rogers and Wells as a part-time member, while simultaneously founding his own business consultant firm, the Clark Company. The Business Records sub-series documents his activities in both, which made use of the foreign contacts he had made and the knowledge of government regulatory agencies he had acquired. This sub-series reflects an interest in Iraqi oil continuing throughout the 1980s and 1990s, seen in several places and especially in the Iraq/Aqaba Pipeline Project proposal for a pipeline from the oilfields of Iraq to the port of Aqaba in Jordan. Also of interest is the proposal of the U.S. Three Gorges Working Group, a consortium of American companies, for a hydroelectric project on the Yangtze River in the People's Republic of China. The Subject File sub-series includes retrospective assessments of the Reagan presidential administration. It also reflects Clark's identity as a Catholic and as a social conservative, and especially his activity in opposing legalized abortion. Through 1990 Clark maintained the practice he had established in 1981 of separate alphabetical correspondence files for each year.
The Audiovisual File is especially notable for its photographs of Clark with Reagan and with other dignitaries. Most of these photographs are of professional quality.
National Security Council (U.S.); Reagan, Ronald.; United States. Department of State.; United States. Department of the Interior.; California--Politics and government--1951-; Public lands--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--1981-1989.; United States--Politics and government--1981-1989.
- California Governor's Office File, 1966-1969
  Scope and Contents note
  Papers of William P. Clark as successively Cabinet Secretary and Executive Secretary to Governor Ronald Reagan, 1967-1969
  - Cabinet Secretary personal file, 1967 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Biographical data, correspondence, memoranda and press coverage
  - Executive Secretary appointment, 1967 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    Press release and press coverage. Includes material on resignation of Philip Battaglia from position
  - Drew Pearson controversy related to Battaglia resignation, 1967 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    Press releases, notes and press coverage
  - Executive Secretary appointment congratulatory letters, 1967 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Executive Secretary personal file
    - Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 1: 5, Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Invitations declined, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 2: 2-3)
    - Press coverage, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 2: 4-5)
    - Ronald Reagan speeches, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Cabinet meetings
    Minutes, agenda and meeting materials
    - 1967 January (Box-folder 2: 7)
    - 1967 February (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - 1967 March (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - 1967 April (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - 1967 May (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - 1967 June (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - 1967 July (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - 1967 November (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - 1967 December (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - 1968 January (Box-folder 4: 4)
    - 1968 February (Box-folder 4: 5)
    - 1968 March (Box-folder 4: 6)
    - 1968 April (Box-folder 4: 7)
    - 1968 May (Box-folder 4: 8)
    - 1968 June (Box-folder 4: 9)
    - 1968 July (Box-folder 4: 10)
    - 1968 August (Box-folder 4: 11)
    - 1968 September (Box-folder 4: 12)
    - 1968 October (Box-folder 4: 13)
    - 1968 November (Box-folder 4: 14)
    - 1968 December (Box-folder 4: 15)
    - 1969 January (Box-folder 4: 16)
  - Agriculture and Services Agency memoranda
    - 1967 (Box-folder 4: 17)
    - 1968 (Box-folder 4: 18)
    - 1969 (Box-folder 4: 19)
  - Business and Transportation Agency memoranda
    - 1967 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - 1968 (Box-folder 5: 2)
    - 1969 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Department of Finance memoranda
    - 1967 (Box-folder 5: 4)
    - 1968 (Box-folder 5: 5)
    - 1969 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Health and Welfare Agency memoranda
    - 1967 (Box-folder 5: 7)
    - 1968 (Box-folder 6: 1, Box-folder 5: 8-9)
    - 1969 (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - Resources Agency memoranda
    - 1967 (Box-folder 6: 3)
    - 1968 (Box-folder 6: 4-5)
    - 1969 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - Miscellaneous agency memoranda, 1968 (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - Governor's Office reorganization memoranda
    - 1967 (Box-folder 6: 8)
    - 1968 (Box-folder 6: 9)
  - Memoranda by Clark to Governor's Office staff, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 6: 10)
  - Schedules
    Includes associated press releases
    - 1968 November (Box-folder 7: 1)
    - 1968 December (Box-folder 7: 2)
    - 1969 January (Box-folder 7: 3)
  - Creative Society file
    Material related to "Creative Society" theme of Reagan governorship
    - Memoranda and speech drafts, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 7: 4)
    - Reagan speech press releases, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 7: 5)
    - Printed background materials (Box-folder 7: 6)
  - Television interview of Clark, 1968 March (Box-folder 8: 1)
    Notes and preparatory materials
  - Miscellaneous printed matter (Box-folder 8: 2)
  - Miscellany (Box-folder 8: 3)
    Letters, notes, press releases and "Thanks" license plates commemorating Reagan election
  - Resignation, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 8: 4)
    Press release and letters
- California Judicial File, 1969-1981
  Papers of William P. Clark as successively Judge of the San Luis Obispo County Superior Court, Associate Justice of the California Second District Court of Appeals, and Associate Justice of the California Supreme Court, 1969-1981
  - Biographical data, 1969-1979 (Box-folder 8: 5)
    Resumes and press coverage. Includes California College of Trial Judges certificate and articles about Clark family
  - Appointment as Judge of the San Luis Obispo County Superior Court, 1969
    - Press coverage (Box-folder 8: 6)
      Includes press releases and oath of office
    - Congratulatory letters (Box-folder 8: 7)
  - Judicial election, 1970
    California judges were appointed but required to obtain voter approval in general elections to retain office
    - General (Box-folder 8: 8)
      Correspondence, memoranda, notes and background material
    - Campaign literature (Box-folder 9: 1)
    - Official documents (Box-folder 9: 2)
      Candidate statements, reports of campaign expenditures, and certificate of election
    - Congratulatory letters (Box-folder 9: 3)
  - Appointment as Associate Justice, California Second District Court of Appeals, 1971 (Box-folder 9: 4)
    Press release, correspondence, oath of office and press coverage
  - Appointment as Associate Justice, California Supreme Court, 1973
    - General (Box-folder 9: 5)
      Correspondence, memoranda and oath of office proceedings
    - State Bar of California report on nomination of Clark (Box-folder 9: 6)
  - Judicial election, 1974 (Box-folder 9: 7)
    Correspondence, memoranda, candidate statement, financial disclosure, and certificate of election
  - Appointment books
    - 1970 (Box-folder 9: 8)
    - 1971 (Box-folder 10: 1)
    - 1972 (Box-folder 10: 2)
    - 1973 (Box-folder 10: 3)
    - 1974 (Box-folder 10: 4)
    - 1975 (Box-folder 10: 5)
    - 1976 (Box-folder 11: 1)
  - Financial disclosure statements
    - 1974 (Box-folder 11: 2)
    - 1975 (Box-folder 11: 3)
    - 1976 (Box-folder 11: 4)
    - 1977 (Box-folder 11: 5)
    - 1978 (Box-folder 11: 6)
    - 1979 (Box-folder 11: 7)
    - 1980 (Box-folder 11: 8)
  - Speech file
    - Notes and drafts (Box-folder 11: 9)
    - Background material (Box-folder 12: 1)
  - Correspondence, 1969-1981
    - A (Box-folder 12: 2)
    - B (Box-folder 12: 3)
    - C (Box-folder 12: 4)
    - Clark family (Box-folder 12: 5)
    - D (Box-folder 12: 6)
    - Defense Research Institute (Box-folder 12: 7)
    - E (Box-folder 12: 8)
    - F (Box-folder 12: 9)
    - Foundation for Economic Education (Box-folder 12: 10)
    - G (Box-folder 12: 11)
    - Glendale University College of Law (Box-folder 12: 12)
    - Gould, Charles L. (Box-folder 12: 13)
    - H (Box-folder 12: 14)
    - Hastings College of the Law (Box-folder 13: 1)
    - I (Box-folder 13: 2)
    - Institute for Contemporary Studies (Box-folder 13: 3)
    - J (Box-folder 13: 4)
    - Judicial Council of California (Box-folder 13: 5)
    - K (Box-folder 13: 6)
    - L (Box-folder 13: 7)
    - Loyola Law School (Box-folder 13: 8)
    - Luce, Gordon C. (Box-folder 13: 9)
    - M (Box-folder 13: 10)
    - McGeorge School of Law (Box-folder 13: 11)
    - N (Box-folder 14: 1)
    - O (Box-folder 14: 2)
    - P (Box-folder 14: 3)
    - Q (Box-folder 14: 4)
    - R (Box-folder 14: 5)
    - Reagan, Ronald (Box-folder 14: 6)
    - Reed, Thomas C. (Box-folder 14: 7)
    - S (Box-folder 14: 8)
    - Sherriffs, Alex C. (Box-folder 14: 9)
    - T (Box-folder 14: 10)
    - U (Box-folder 14: 11)
    - V (Box-folder 14: 12)
    - W (Box-folder 14: 13)
    - Weinberger, Caspar (Box-folder 14: 14)
    - Y (Box-folder 14: 15)
    - Z (Box-folder 14: 16)
  - State Bar of California rules and regulations, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 14: 17)
  - California Supreme Court internal memoranda and judicial opinion statistics, 1971-1980 (Box-folder 14: 18)
  - Subject file
    - Bird, Rose, 1978
      Material on election to determine retention of Rose Bird as Chief Justice of the California Supreme Court, 1978
      - General (Box-folder 15: 1)
        Correspondence and memoranda. Includes No on Bird Committee campaign literature
      - Press coverage (Box-folder 15: 2-3)
    - Birkenhead et al. vs. City of Berkeley, 1973 (Box-folder 15: 4)
      Petitions and decisions in Superior Court of Alameda County case re rent control
    - California Citizens' Commission on Tort Reform, 1977 (Box-folder 15: 5)
      Printed report
    - California judicial system (general)
      - General, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 15: 6)
        Correspondence, memoranda, press releases and California District Attorneys Association publications
      - George Nicholson articles, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 15: 7)
      - Press coverage, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 16: 1-3)
    - Land use, 1975-1980 (Box-folder 16: 4)
      Legal petition and printed articles
    - Law (general), 1971-1980 (Box-folder 16: 5)
      Printed articles and serial issues
    - Lillie, Mildred L., 1980 (Box-folder 16: 6)
      Biographical data and printed articles
    - McComb, Marshall, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 17: 1)
      Correspondence, notes and legal documents re conservatorship of McComb
    - Mosk vs. Superior Court of Los Angeles County, 1979 (Box-folder 17: 2)
      Petition re request of Justice Stanley Mosk to be excused from hearing of the Commission on Judicial Performance
    - People vs. Caudillo, 1978 (Box-folder 17: 3)
      California Supreme Court decision in case re "great bodily injury" as aggravating factor in sentencing
    - People vs. Drew, 1978 (Box-folder 17: 4)
      Dissenting Clark opinion in California Supreme Court case re mental state defense
    - People vs. Remiro and Little, 1979 (Box-folder 17: 5)
      Petition in California Court of Appeals case re Symbionese Liberation Army members
    - People vs. Tanner
      In this 1978 case the California Supreme Court in a 4-3 decision (Clark dissenting) overturned a California law making a prison sentence mandatory for use of a gun during commission of a crime. Public reaction resulted in Commission on Judicial Performance hearings. The following year the Court reheard the case and, in another 4-3 decision, reversed its earlier ruling
      - Draft opinions by Chief Justice Rose Bird (Box-folder 17: 6)
      - Draft opinions by Justice William Clark (Box-folder 17: 7)
      - Draft opinions by Justice Wiley Manuel (Box-folder 17: 8)
      - Draft opinions by Justice Frank Newman (Box-folder 17: 9)
      - Draft opinions by Justice Matthew Tobriner (Box-folder 17: 10)
      - Comprehensive draft opinions (Box-folder 17: 11)
      - Internal Court memoranda and statements, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 18: 1)
      - Working material and miscellany, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 18: 2)
      - Commission on Judicial Performance hearings, 1979 (Box-folder 18: 3)
        Correspondence and memoranda
      - Press coverage, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 18: 4-6, Box-folder 19: 1-2)
    - Pueblo de Los Angeles Historical Monument Commission, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 19: 3)
      Correspondence
    - Rancheros Visitadores, 1979 (Box-folder 19: 4)
      Membership book
    - United States vs. The Progressive et al., 1979 (Box-folder 19: 5)
      Legal document in federal court case re prior restraint on publication
    - Ventura County Fair Junior Livestock Auction, 1974 (Box-folder 19: 6)
  - Insurance records (Box-folder 19: 7)
  - Medical records (Box-folder 19: 8)
  - Miscellaneous financial records (Box-folder 19: 9)
  - Telephone numbers (Box-folder 19: 10)
  - Miscellaneous printed matter (Box-folder 20: 1-2)
  - Miscellany (Box-folder 20: 3)
  - Retirement, 1981
    - General (Box-folder 20: 4)
      Correspondence, memoranda and printed matter re winding up judicial matters and expressions of appreciation
    - Background material (Box-folder 20: 5-6)
      Memoranda re retirement compensation and California Judicial Retirement Handbook
  - Farewell dinner, San Francisco, California, 1981 March 22 (Box-folder 20: 7)
    Correspondence, memoranda and tribute by Justice Frank Richardson
- United States Department of State File, 1981-1982
  Papers of William P. Clark as United States Deputy Secretary of State, 1981-1982
  - Appointment as Deputy Secretary of State, 1981
    - General (Box-folder 21: 1)
      Announcement, press releases, and financial disclosure and security clearance documents
    - Confirmation hearing before U.S. Senate Foreign Relations Committee, 1981 February 2-3 (Box-folder 21: 2)
      Prepared statement, notes and talking points, transcript of hearing, and roll call vote
    - Press coverage (Box-folder 21: 3-4)
  - Personnel documents and official background documents, including press releases and press conference transcripts (Box-folder 21: 5)
  - Biographical file (Box-folder 21: 6-7, Box-folder 22: 1)
    Biographical data and press coverage
  - Appointment book, 1981 (Box-folder 22: 2)
  - Schedules
    - 1981 January-April (Box-folder 22: 3)
    - 1981 May-August (Box-folder 22: 4)
    - 1981 September-December (Box-folder 22: 5)
    - 1982 January (Box-folder 22: 6)
  - Speeches and events file
    Correspondence, memoranda, speeches and press coverage
    - American College of Trial Lawyers Northern California Chapter dinner, San Francisco, California, 1981 May 29 (Box-folder 22: 7)
      Includes speech
    - San Francisco Law School commencement address, San Francisco, California, 1981 May 30 (Box-folder 23: 1)
    - Visit to South Africa and South-West Africa (Namibia), 1981 June 10-12 (Box-folder 23: 2)
    - Visit to France, Belgium, West Germany and Austria, 1981 June 14-15 (Box-folder 23: 3)
    - Dialogkongress Westeuropa-USA, Alpbach, Austria, 1981 June 21 (Box-folder 23: 4)
    - Austrian Foreign Policy Association meeting, Vienna, Austria, 1981 June 24 (Box-folder 23: 5)
    - San Luis Obispo Mozart Festival, San Luis Obispo, California, 1981 August 2 (Box-folder 23: 6)
    - Judge Arthur K. Marshall retirement dinner, Los Angeles, California, 1981 September 16 (Box-folder 23: 7)
    - Pasadena Bar Association meeting, Pasadena, California, 1981 September 17 (Box-folder 23: 8)
    - St. Thomas More Award presentation, San Francisco, California, 1981 September 21 (Box-folder 23: 9)
      Includes remarks
    - Student Conference on U.S. Affairs, U.S. Military Academy, West Point, New York, 1981 November 18 (Box-folder 23: 10)
    - Visit to Great Britain, Ireland and West Germany, 1981 December 2-8 (Box-folder 23: 11)
    - Jewish National Fund of Los Angeles Chanukah banquet, Los Angeles, California, 1981 December 27 (Box-folder 23: 12)
  - Chronological correspondence (outgoing letters)
    - 1981 January (Box-folder 24: 1)
    - 1981 February (Box-folder 24: 2)
    - 1981 March (Box-folder 24: 3)
    - 1981 April (Box-folder 24: 4)
    - 1981 May (Box-folder 24: 5)
    - 1981 June (Box-folder 24: 6)
    - 1981 July (Box-folder 25: 1)
    - 1981 August (Box-folder 25: 2)
    - 1981 September (Box-folder 25: 3)
    - 1981 October (Box-folder 25: 4)
    - 1981 November (Box-folder 25: 5)
    - 1981 December (Box-folder 25: 6)
    - 1981 Christmas gift acknowledgments (Box-folder 25: 7)
  - Alphabetical correspondence, 1981
    - A (Box-folder 25: 8)
    - Abshire, David M. (Box-folder 25: 9)
    - Allen, Richard V. (Box-folder 25: 10)
    - Amery, Julian (Box-folder 25: 11)
    - B (Box-folder 26: 1-2)
    - Baker, Warren J. (Box-folder 26: 3)
    - Baldrige, Malcolm (Box-folder 26: 4)
    - Bea, Carlos (Box-folder 26: 5)
    - Bernstein, Stan (Box-folder 26: 6)
    - Bertain, G. Joseph, Jr. (Box-folder 26: 7)
    - Botha, R. F. (South African foreign minister) (Box-folder 26: 8)
    - Bravo, Francisco (Box-folder 26: 9)
    - Brooks, Claudia (Box-folder 26: 10)
    - Brower, Charles N. (Box-folder 26: 11)
    - Bruinsma, Theo. A. (Box-folder 26: 12)
    - Burger, Warren (Box-folder 26: 13)
    - Bush, George (Box-folder 26: 14)
    - C (Box-folder 26: 15, Box-folder 27: 1)
    - Campbell, Dennis (Box-folder 27: 2)
    - Carlucci, Frank C. (Box-folder 27: 3)
    - Casey, William J. (Box-folder 27: 4)
    - Clausen, Don (Box-folder 27: 5)
    - Cranston, Alan (Box-folder 27: 6)
    - D (Box-folder 27: 7)
    - Dart, Justin (Box-folder 27: 8)
    - Deaver, Michael (Box-folder 27: 9)
    - Del Junco, Tirso (Box-folder 27: 10)
    - Deukmejian, George (Box-folder 27: 11)